Finding Aid for Catherine Kemmering collection
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Catherine Kemmering collection 1976-1988 and 1995
Kemmering, Catherine
3 linear feet
2013072 Aa 2
Collection of scrapbooks and artifacts related to the Michigan Womyn's Music Festival; also a photo album with photographs from the 1978 National ERA Rally in Washington, D.C.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Material was donated by the Estate of Catherine Kemmering (Donor no. 10932 ) in May 2013.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research. All photographs are prohibited from duplication.
The Michigan Womyn's Music Festival is the oldest and largest continuing outdoor women-only festival. It was founded in 1976 by Lisa Vogel, her sister Kristie Vogel, and friend Mary Kindig who conceived the idea of organizing a women's outdoor music festival after attending the outdoor Midwest Women's Festival and the in-door Boston Women's Music Festival. To help create the Michigan festival, Lisa, Kristie and Mary formed the We Want the Music Collective. The collective raised money, booked performances, distributed information and tickets. The first festival took place on August 20-22, 1976 in Mt. Pleasant, on the 120 acres of land rented by the Collective. Singer-songwriter Holly Near and singer Teresa Trull were among the first Michigan Womyn's Music Festival performers. While the organizers expected about 1,000 people to attend, the first Festival was attended by approximately 2,000. After the first year's success, it was decided to extend the length of the Festival to 4 days. The length of the festival was extended to 5 days by 1986. Between 1977 and 1981 the Festival was held in Hesperia, Mich. In 1982 the Festival moved to a 650-acre location between Hart and Ludington in Oceana County, Mich.
The week-long Festival has grown in number of attendees and diversity of performances, activities, and educational and vocational workshops. Over the years the festival has become ethnically diverse and includes "Womyn of Color"-only space and a "Jewish Womyn's Tent." The festival is family friendly and provides childcare, including a camp for boys aged 5 to 10 (boys aged 4 and under are allowed within the festival). Women volunteers serve as builders, electricians, sound workers, mechanics, security guards, make meals, and provide daycare during the festival.
After the festival, volunteers dismantle constructions, completely remove all non-organic materials from the land, and bury electrical boxes.
The collection includes scrapbooks and programs of the Michigan Womyn's Music Festival held between the 1st Festival (1976) and the 13th Festival (1988) -- with the exception of the 11th Festival (1986) -- and the 20th Festival (1995). Scrapbooks include photographs, maps, memoranda, correspondence, and ephemera. Also two cotton shirts from the 1982 and 1984 festivals.
In addition, the collection includes a photo album with photographs taken during the 1978 National ERA Rally in Washington, D.C.
Subjects:
Michigan Womyn's Music Festival.; Women's music festivals--Michigan.
Genre Terms:
Photo albums.; Scrapbooks.
- Catherine Kemmering collection
  - 1st: August 20-22, 1976 (Box 1)
  - 2nd: August 25-28, 1977 (Box 1)
  - 3rd: August 17-20, 1978 (Box 1)
  - 4th: August 23-26, 1979 (Box 1)
  - 5th: August 14-17, 1980 (Box 1)
  - 6th: August 13-16, 1981 (Box 2)
  - 7th: August 12-15, 1982 (Box 2)
  - 7th Michigan Womyn's Music Festival cotton shirt, 1982 (Box 2)
  - 8th: August 11-14, 1983 (Box 2)
  - 9th: August 9-12, 1984 (Box 3)
  - 9th Michigan Womyn's Music Festival cotton shirt, 1984 (Box 3)
  - 10th: August 8-11, 1985 (Box 3)
  - 12th: August 12-16, 1987 (Box 3)
  - 13th: August 10-14, 1988 (Box 3)
  - 20th: August 8-13, 1995 (Box 3)
  - 1978 National ERA Rally (Box 3)